Jonathan A. DeCastro

CONTACT INFORMATION

1261 Warren Rd. Apt. A Ithaca, NY 14850

github: github.com/jadecastro

t: +1-585-425-7184 e: jad455@cornell.edu w: jadecastro.github.io

RESEARCH **INTERESTS** My research interests are in the construction of provably-correct controllers for dynamical systems, enabling complex tasks to be verified for a wide class of complex robots. I am investigating both composition of continuous controllers for verified high-level control and the automatic discovery of specification revisions for guaranteeing controller execution in dynamic environments. My work draws from a variety of technical domains, including control theory, optimization, and formal methods.

EDUCATION

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

Ph.D., Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering

2015-Present

Advisor: Prof. Hadas Kress-Gazit

Graduate Minors: Computer Science, Computational Science and Engineering

M.S., Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering

2011-2014

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA M.S., Mechanical Engineering

2001-2003

B.S. (with Honors), Mechanical Engineering 1996-2001

RELEVANT Courses

Applied Math and Optimization: Linear Systems, Probability, Mathematical Programming, Convex Optimization, Heuristic Methods for Optimization

Controls and Systems: Hybrid Systems, Robust Control, Stochastic Control, Multivariable Control Robotics and Dynamics: Intermediate Dynamics, Robot Learning, Autonomous Mobile Robots, Robotic Manipulation

INDUSTRY AND RESEARCH **EXPERIENCE**

Graduate Research Assistant, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2011–Present

Verifiable Robotics Research Group

- Developed algorithms in C++, Python and MATLAB for automated, correct-by-construction synthesis of controllers for robots with nonlinear dynamics through application of formal methods and optimization
- Developed a novel approach to automatically synthesize revisions to robot mission specifications that cannot be realized and explain these revisions to the user via auto-generated feedback
- Authored 7 publications featured in international conference proceedings, workshops and robotics journals

Lead Engineer, Impact Technologies, LLC., Rochester, NY

July 2008-August 2011

Control and Prediction Group

- Conducted independent research on control algorithms and simulation tools for flight control and diagnostic systems and submarine navigation
- Awarded four Phase 1 and two Phase 2 Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grants as Principal Investigator
- Composed technical reports and conference papers, presented to customers and stakeholders, and mentored co-op students

Research Scientist, NASA Glenn Research Center, Cleveland, OH

July 2003-July 2008

Intelligent Control and Autonomy Branch

- Designed and coded Commercial Modular Aero-Propulsion System Simulation (C-MAPSS), a MATLABbased "virtual" aircraft engine serving to extend accessibility of such models to a wide arena of researchers
- Investigated control algorithms for in-flight aircraft control reconfiguration during emergencies
- Implemented and tested various control techniques in scaled engine component test rigs

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- **J. A. DeCastro** and H. Kress-Gazit. Synthesis of nonlinear continuous controllers for verifiably-correct high-level, reactive behaviors. *International Journal of Robotics Research*, 34(3):378–394, 2015. doi:10.1177/0278364914557736
- **J. A. DeCastro**, R. Ehlers, M. Rungger, A. Balkan, P. Tabuada, and H. Kress-Gazit. Dynamics-based reactive synthesis and automated revisions for high-level robot control. (submitted) *CoRR*, abs/1410.6375, 2014. arXiv:http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.6375.
- X. Zhang, L. Tang and **J. A. DeCastro**. Robust fault diagnosis of aircraft engines: a nonlinear adaptive estimation-based approach. *IEEE Trans. on Control Systems Technology*, 21(3):861–868, 2013. doi:10.1109/TCST.2012.2187057.
- **J. A. DeCastro**. Rate-based model predictive control of turbofan engine clearance. *AIAA Journal of Propulsion and Power*. 23(4):804–813, 2007. doi:10.2514/1.25846

AIAA NOS Best Young Professional Paper

SELECTED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- **J. A. DeCastro**, J. Alonso-Mora, V. Raman, D. Rus and H. Kress-Gazit. Collision-free reactive mission and motion planning for multi-robot systems. To appear in: *Proceedings of the 17th International Symposium on Robotics Research (ISRR)*, Sestri Levante, Italy, September 12–15, 2015.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, V. Raman and H. Kress-Gazit. Dynamics-driven adaptive abstraction for reactive high-level mission and motion planning. In: *Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA 2015)*, Seattle, WA, USA, May 26–30, 2015.
- **J. A. DeCastro** and H. Kress-Gazit. Guaranteeing reactive high-level behaviors for robots with complex dynamics. In: *Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2013)*, Tokyo, Japan, November 3–8, 2013.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, L. Tang, B. Zhang and G. Vachtsevanos. A safety verification approach to fault-tolerant aircraft supervisory control. In: *Proceedings of the AIAA Guidance, Navigation, and Control Conference*, Portland, OR, USA, August 8–11, 2011.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, L. Tang, C. S. Byington and D. E. Culley. Analysis of fault-tolerance and decentralization concepts for distributed engine control. In: *Proceedings of the 45th AIAA Joint Propulsion Conference & Exhibit*, Denver, CO, USA, August 2–5, 2009.

ASME Propulsion Best Paper

J. A. DeCastro, J. S. Litt, and D. K. Frederick. A modular aero-propulsion system simulation of a large commercial aircraft engine. In: *Proceedings of the 44th AIAA/ASME/SAE/ASEE Joint Propulsion Conference & Exhibit*, Hartford, CT USA, July 21–23, 2008.

WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS **J. A. DeCastro**. Mission possible: guaranteeing reactive missions for complex robots. In: *ICRA 2015 Ph.D. Forum*, Seattle, WA, USA, May 26, 2015.

TEACHING AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE Teaching Assistant, Autonomous Mobile Robots, Cornell University

Spring 2015

• Taught lab sessions, delivered occasional lectures, graded code and reports (36 students)

Mentor, Undergraduate Research, Cornell University

Spring 2015

- Mentored seven undergraduates for two entries in the 2015 Soft Robotics Design Competition
- Earned First Prize (out of 82 teams) and Honorable Mention for outstanding project idea

Instructor, System Modeling, Rochester Institute of Technology

Winter 2010-2011

• Administered, lectured and graded a senior- and graduate-level course

SERVICE AND OUTREACH Workshop Organizer, "Command Your Own Robot"

2014, 2015

- Organized and lead a hands-on robotics workshop as part of the **Expanding Your Horizons (EYH)** conference for middle-school girls interested in math and science
- Supervised a team of four to lead the activities and introduce students to opportunities for further education and careers in STEM fields

Voting Member, Cornell Graduate and Professional Student Assembly

2013-2014

• Organized several events for facilitating discussion of issues of interest (e.g. student life, compensation), between graduate students and university administration

Reviewer,

| | 210 / 10 / 10 / 10 / 10 / 10 / 10 / 10 / | |
|------------|--|------------------|
| | • IEEE Conf. on Event-Based Control, Communication, and Signal Processing (EBCCSP) | 2015 |
| | International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) | 2014, 2015 |
| | • American Control Conference (ACC) | 2014 |
| | • IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics | 2011, 2012, 2013 |
| | ASME Turbo Expo | 2005, 2007, 2010 |
| Hovorg | Trevel Count to ICD A in Couttle WA annual by IEEE DAC and NCE | 2015 |
| Honors and | Travel Grant to ICRA in Seattle, WA; sponsored by IEEE RAS and NSF | 2015 |
| AWARDS | Cornell MAE Fellowship, a merit-based award to incoming Ph.D. students | 2011–2012 |
| | ASME Propulsion Best Paper Award | 2009 |
| | NASA Group Achievement Award for outstanding group accomplishment (C-MAPSS Tear | n) 2009 |
| | NASA Space Act Award for an outstanding technical contribution | 2007 |
| | AIAA Best Young Professional Paper awarded by the Northern Ohio Section of AIAA | 2007 |